Guide to the Richard F. C. Hartley Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Richard F. C. Hartley papers
1816-1881
MS 646
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
4.25
(6 boxes)
Correspondence and business papers of Captain Richard F. C. Hartley, shipping firm owner of Saco, Maine, mainly relating to voyages of the ships Messenger and Devonshire. Also included are Samuel Hartley's memo booklets for the sloop Packet of Saco, 1816-1838. An addition to the collection includes documents of ships owned by Richard Hartley involved in the guano trade between Peru and other countries.
Hartley, Richard F. C.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired by purchase.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
Arranged primarily by type of material.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of business correspondence and other papers of Captain Richard F. C. Hartley, shipping firm owner of Saco, Maine. It also includes the papers of Samuel Hartley.
The papers of Samuel Hartley consist of eighteen memo books of the sloop "Packet of Saco" sailing out of Boston. They contain accounts, records of cargoes and business to be transacted, notes on correspondence and navigation, lists of passengers, and so forth.
The correspondence of Richard F. C. Hartley deals with orders for cargoes, the purchase of ships and hiring of crews, financial matters, insurance policies, and related matters. There are letters from several captains reporting on their voyages and on repairs to their ships, including a substantial number of letters from Captain Sedgley recording two voyages (1869-1871) of the "Devonshire" to Europe, China, South East Asia, and Japan. Other letters record voyages of the "Messenger" to Europe and Asia.
Hartley's diary for 1870 covers a business trip to the West Coast. It contains notes about both business and social activities, as well as some financial records. The rest of Hartley's papers deal with various of his ships. There is a memo book for the "Messenger" for the years 1863-1872 containing lists of crew members, supplies, and equipment, financial records, et cetera. The other ships' papers consist of legal and financial materials such as insurance policies, bills and receipts, checks, and related items. The largest groups of papers pertain to the "Messenger" and the "Devonshire," while smaller amounts of material relate to the "A. Hammond," the "J. Montgomery," and others. The papers are arranged by ship.
The memo books of Samuel Hartley were acquired by Yale University by purchase in 1967.
An addition to the collection includes documents of ships owned by Richard Hartley involved in the guano trade between Peru and other countries. Also included are documents related to trade throught San Francisco and New Orleans.
Biographical / Historical
Richard F. C. Hartley was born around 1808. He was from Saco, Maine, where he was engaged in the shipping business. Hartley made voyages all across the world, transporting European Mormons to the United States in 1854 and traveling to Australia in 1860. He died at sea in 1897 after a long illness.
Business; Guano industry; China; Japan; Maine -- Commerce; New England; Peru; Businessmen; Hartley, Richard F. C.; Hartley, Samuel; Devonshire (Ship); Messenger (Ship); Packet (Sloop)
- Original Accession
  - Samuel Hartley: memo books for the sloop "Packet of Saco", 1816 May-1838 January (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Richard F. C. Hartley
    - Correspondence, 1865-1881, undated (Box 1, Folder 3-10)
    - Diary, 1870 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Memo book for the ship Messenger, 1863-1872 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Ships' legal and financial papers
      - A. Hammond, 1875-1881 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - D. W. Vaughan, 1859 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - Delhi, 1873 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - Devonshire, 1867-1875 (Box 2, Folder 14 - 15)
      - J. W. Montgomery, 1867-1869 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      - Messenger, 1864-1875, undated (Box 2, Folder 17 - 20)
      - Restless, 1873 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Windward, 1867 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Miscellaneous, 1865-1899, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Additional Material, Circa 1854-1884; Accession 2009-M-086
  Scope and Contents
  This accession includes correspondence, labor agreements, invoices, insurance contracts, and other financial documents relating to the operations of various ships, primarily employed in the guano trade, owned by Richard F. C. Hartley of Saco, Maine. Hartley's ships called at ports in North and South America, Europe, and Asia. Also included are shipping documents relating to trade through San Francisco and New Orleans.
  Arrangement
  Arranged primarily by type of material.
  - Letters to Richard Hartley from captains of his ships, Circa 1866-1873 (Box 2, Folder 1-5)
    A significant number of these letters are from a ship captain named Waldo Hill.
  - Letters to Richard Hartley from insurance brokers, shipping merchants, and captains, 1864-1880 (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
  - Correspondence and related documents from shipping agents and insurance brokers relating to guano cargo, 1865-1875 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Insurance, contracts, and other financial records relating to the ship Messenger and the bark Devonshire, Circa 1864-1879 (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
  - Insurance, bills of cargo, tug boat receipts, ballast lists, and invoices, 1863-1877 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - Invoices for goods and services received, Circa 1864-1881 (Box 2, Folder 8-11)
  - Invoices and customs forms from various ships, 1864-1881 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Ships include Sterling, Messenger, and Devonshire.
  - Agreements between ship masters and crew, Circa 1854-1884 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)